Guide to the Ervin J. Nalos Papers, 1939-1959
Department of Special Collections
Ervin J. Nalos Papers,
1939-1959
Special Collections M801
Nalos, Ervin J.
3 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Gift of Ervin J. Nalos, 1995
BIOGRAPHY
Ervin J. Nalos, a naturalized United States citizen, was born September 10, 1924 in Prague. Dr. Nalos' undergraduate study was done at the University of British Columbia in Vancouver, B.A. Sc., 1946. Graduate work, M.A. Sc., 1947, was also started in Vancouver. His Ph.D. in electrical engineering, 1951, was earned at Stanford, where he worked at the Stanford Microwave Laboratory. Dr. Nalos received the Baker Award, Institute of Radio Engineering in 1959. His professional career encompasses: research associate, microwave physics, 1950-54; group leader, microwave tube development and research at Microwave Laboratory, General Electric, California, 1954-59; scientific representative to Europe, 1959-62; staff engineer, Office of Vice President, Research and Development, Boeing Aerospace Co., 1962-69; manager of applied technology, Military Airplane Systems Division, 1969-71; supervisor, civil and commercial systems, 1971-78; supervisor, electromagnetics, Boeing Defense and Space Group 1978-. Dr. Nalos' research has been in electron physics and electronics, high power microwave devices and electromagnetic scattering.
The following quote was sent by Dr. Nalos: "Dr. Ervin Nalos was part of an important offshoot of the pioneering work on high power klystrons which Dr. Ginzton and his team initiated to power the Linear Accelerator project of Dr. Hansen in the 1946-50 period. While a PhD student and Research Associate, he and Prof. Marvin Chodorow, inspired by the work of J. R. Pierce, reduced to practice the first waveguide loaded Traveling Wave Tube and the first Megawatt Pulsed TWT. This development would not have been possible without the Linac slow wave circuit development and the high power cathode development on the klystron. Combining this capability in a Traveling Wave Circuit provided bandwidth as well as high power, now maturing into a $100 Mill./year industry with many advances and refinements. In a real sense, the high power microwave work during this period in the Stanford Microwave Laboratory, was a real precursor to what is called Silicon Valley, and deserves a real study by a researcher interested in the history of science. In that sense, the material sent to you [Department of Special Collections, Stanford University Libraries] together with other old Microwave Lab reports, should provide an excellent resource. These include original data on the first derivative tube at S and X-band conducted at the GE Microwave Lab at Stanford.
Dr. Nalos, under the direction of Dr. Ginzton, and with some assistance from Dr. John Shaw, also pioneered the first Microwave Lab. Measurements course and the original lecture and lab notes from this series are documented in the collection. en 8/96"
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This collection contains technical information on electron tube research from the years 1939-1959, the major portion being Dr. Nalos' papers from 1945-1959. While there is some correspondence and memos, most of the collection is comprised of technical reports. Many of these reports are handwritten personal notes on experiments and test data collection with some blueprints and photographs; others are printed technical reports. Box 4 contains two disbound binders with tables of contents by Dr. Nalos relating to the Microwave Labs at Stanford. Box 5 contains one disbound binder entitled "High Power TWT Survey." Box 6 contains actual objects relating to electron tubes.
Much of this collection is fragile and should be handled with extreme care. If the researcher finds loose pieces, please bring to the attention of the reference desk.
CONTAINER LIST
- High Power X-Band TWT - Traveling Wave Tube, 1957-1959; internal memos, outside correspondence, blueprints (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Winkler, handwritten summary on 50 kw Klystron, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Double Slot Low Voltage Spatial Harmonic Circuit," Z3032, personal notes, 1957-1958; photograph, calculations, graphs, blueprints (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Some Design Considerations of Solid Beam Loaded Waveguide Circuits For High Power TWT's," technical report, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- E. J. Nalos, F. K. Patton, G. Novick, J. W. Moyer, "Cold Test Studies," 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- R. A. Craig, "Study of Periodic Structures For High-Voltage TWT Operation," 1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Details of Coupler For Megawatt X-Band Traveling-Wave Tube," 1955 (from blueprints) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Patent disclosure letters to patent attorney, General Electric Microwave Lab, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Notes for a slide talk, 1956, Technical Staff for Electron Tube Research, 1956; E. J. Nalos, R. Craig, Equipment Requirements for "High Power TW Program," 1954;; "Investigation of Yoke Type Electromagnets for Beam Focusing," technical report, nd (Box 1, Folder 9)
- S. Hearst for E. J. Nalos, technical report, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- S. Webber, memo - Z5257, 1958, C. Karabats, manufacturing procedure for Z5257, 1959; blueprint, graphs (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Shunt Impedance of Klystron Cavities," technical report, nd (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Blueprints, nd (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Z5257, Z5260, technical data, 1958, R. P. Borghi, Z5083 technical report, 1956-1957; photographs;; blueprint, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "X-Band Driver Tube Test Data," 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- M. Chodorow, E. L. Ginzton and E. J. Nalos, "Debunching Of Electron Beams Constrained By Strong Magnetic Fields," reprint, 1953, "Measurement of Circuit Impedance of Periodically Loaded Structures by Frequency Perturbation," reprint, 1954; E.L. Ginzton and E. J. Nalos, "Shunt Impedance of Klystron Cavities," reprint, 1955;; M. Chodorow and E. J. Nalos, "The Design of High-Power Traveling-Wave Tubes," reprint, 1956;; "A Hybrid Type Traveling-Wave Tube for High-Power Pulsed Amplification," reprint, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- E. J. Nalos, C. G. Lob, "Magnetron Injection Gun," technical report, 1957-1958; photographs, blueprint (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "PM Focussed TWT Tube #1," personal notes, 1956-1958; blueprints (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "Hybrid Type TWT," technical report, 1957-1958; photograph (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "A Hybrid Type TWT, Suitable for High Power Pulsed Amplification," technical report - 2 copies, General Electric Microwave Lab, Nov, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "S Band High Power TW Tube," rough draft, 1955, "Measurement of Circuit Impedance of Periodically Loaded Structures by Frequency Perturbation," reprint, 1954; E. J. Nalos, M. Chodorow, "The Design of High-Power Traveling-Wave Tubes," reprint, 1956; (Box 2, Folder 5)
- "A Hybrid Type Traveling-Wave Tube Suitable For High Power Pulsed Amplification," technical report - personal copy, General Electric Microwave Lab, Mar, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "Some Design Considerations of Solid Beam Loaded Waveguide Circuits For High Power TWT's," technical report, General Electric Microwave Lab, Jan, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- E. J. Nalos, R. M. Phillips, "Permanent Magnet Focusing Suitable for Megawatt Type High Gain Amplifiers," technical memo, General Electric Microwave Lab, Mar, 1957, "Feasibility Study and Investigation of High Perveance Power Amplifiers," General Electric Microwave Lab, nd (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "High Perveance Parallel Beam Studies," 1958-1959; photographs (Box 2, Folder 9)
- E. J. Nalos, C. G. Lob, "A Magnetron Injection Gun For Megawatt-Type Pulsed Microwave Tubes," technical report - personal copy with addendum, General Electric Microwave Lab, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "PM Focused Traveling-Wave Tube #2," personal notes, 1958, Z5242 - "Tests with Non-propag. Section," Jun, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- "Byperiodic Tube," nd (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "Non-Propagating Hybrid Tube," preliminary technical report - personal copy, Mar, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- E. J. Nalos, F. K. Patton, "Periodic Magnetic Focusing Solid Beams In The 10-25 KV Range," technical report, General Electric Microwave Lab, Dec, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- R. M. Phillips, "Study of Lightweight Focusing and High Power TWT Efficiency Improvement," General Microwave Lab, Mar, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- "Multiple Beam Cold Tests," personal notes, nd (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "Lectures on TW Tubes 1956" (Box 3, Folder 5)
- D. A. Watkins, "Topics in Electromagnetic Theory," class notes, nd (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Two Disbound Binders, each with a table of contents - attached as Appendix 1, 2 - titled: "Microwave Labs I," 1939-1956; "Microwave Labs II, Experiments, Stanford, 1946-1953 (Box 4)
- One Disbound Binder titled: "High Power TWT Survey," 1956-1958 (Box 5)
- Objects - electron tube parts (Box 6)